<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the ordinatoin [sic] of an elder and deacons in a baptized congregation in London by N.C.</title>
            <author>Coxe, Nehemiah.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B20783</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6718</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09519223</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09519223</idno>
            <idno type="VID">204450</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B20783)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204450)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1328:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the ordinatoin [sic] of an elder and deacons in a baptized congregation in London by N.C.</title>
                  <author>Coxe, Nehemiah.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Fabian,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Titus I, 5 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Ordination sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:204450:1"/>
            <p> A SERMON PREACHED AT THE ORDINATOIN OF AN <hi>Elder and Deacons</hi> IN A Baptized Congregation In LONDON.</p>
            <p>By <hi>N. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Who is ſufficient for theſe things?</hi>
               <bibl> 2 Cor. 2. 16.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Fabian,</hi> at the Bible in Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, a corner Shop next <hi>Cheap-ſide.</hi> 1681.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:204450:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:204450:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>TITUS 1. 5.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>For this cauſe left I thee in</hi> Crete, <hi>that thou ſhouldest ſet in order the things that are wanting, and ordain Elders in every City, as I had appointed thee.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe general Deſign and Scope of theſe Words, is obvious to the obſervation of every one that reads them; The great Apoſtle of the Gentiles had with good ſucceſs laboured in preaching the Goſpel to the <hi>Cretians;</hi> and being himſelf removed from them, after he had as a wiſe Maſter-builder laid the Foundation of many Churches of Chriſtians in <hi>Crete,</hi> he left <hi>Titus</hi> among them to build there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; And while he was reſident there, <hi>Paul</hi> ſends this <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to him, to remind him of that Service for Chriſt in his Churches that he had left upon his Hands; whereby he doth not only quicken him to his Work, but alſo furniſhes him with full and clear Directions for the right ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement thereof.</p>
            <p>In the Account that our Text gives of the Reaſon for which <hi>Paul</hi> left <hi>Titus</hi> in <hi>Grete;</hi> the Service which he was there to be imployed in is ſet down.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:204450:3"/>
               <item>1. In more general and comprehenſive terms, <hi>That thou ſhouldeſt ſet in order the things which are wanting.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. In a more particular Account of one ſpecial Charge left upon him, <hi>And ordain Elders in every City, as I had appointed thee.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>That which we have do in the firſt Place, is briefly to open to you what needs explication in the words.</p>
            <p>The Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is rendred <hi>ſet in order,</hi> is no where elſe uſed in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, nor in the Verſion of the Old by the <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuagint</hi> that I can find: divers learned Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters do here render it by <hi>Corrigas, that thou ſhouldeſt correct;</hi> And <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in his Notes, frames a word more expreſſive of its Emphaſis, <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigas,</hi> which imports to correct with accuracy and exactneſs; as one that goes over a Work again, that he may be ſure to leave no blemiſh upon it, or defect in it. Some underſtand this part of <hi>Titus</hi> his Charge to reſpect the correction of the manners of the <hi>Cretians</hi> by reproof and ſound Doctrine, and with this ſenſe the <hi>Arabick Verſion</hi> fully concurs, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t res vitioſas corrigas; That thou ſhouldst correct the things that are faulty;</hi> And it is evident in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel of the Epiſtle, That this was one part of his Work: But I conceive this is not ſo immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, q. d. <hi>Supercor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigo,</hi> quod plus eſt quam <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigo,</hi> &amp; ea quae aliquâ ex par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te correcta ſunt ad limam, &amp; ſummam li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neam perduco. <hi>Heinſ. in loc.</hi>
               </note> intended by this term, but rather, The ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement and diſpoſing of things relating to the Offices and Government in the Houſe of God, and the Order of their Communion in the Church who were Members of it, in a full and exact agreement with the Rule of Chriſt's Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment; which the Apoſtle had not time to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:204450:3"/> bring to perfection during his ſtay with them: And this ſenſe very well agrees with the uſe of a term of near affinity with this in our Text <hi>(viz.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) in <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 10. where the Days of the Goſpel are called <hi>the Times of Reformation;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in them the State of the Church is brought to its utmoſt perfection here on Earth, and all that was wanting in the Law, is fully ſupplied in the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>The Edification and Beauty of the Church is much concerned in her <hi>Order,</hi> not ſuch an Order as Superſtition will dictate, or litigious Nicety contend for, but ſuch as we have already deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; which ſets her in a conformity with Chriſt's Will; and particularly the filling up of the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which he hath appointed, with Perſons duly qualified for the adminiſtration of them, and the regular acting both of Officers and Members in their reſpective places.</p>
            <p>The particular Charge given to <hi>Titus</hi> is, To <hi>ordain Elders in every City:</hi> This is to be explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by conference with <hi>Act.</hi> 14. 23. where the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Apoſtles themſelves is recorded, <hi>And having ordained them Elders in every Church,</hi> &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is the ſame in theſe Texts: The Converts in every City were not then ſo numerous but they might conveniently <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Et cum ſuftragiis cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſent. <hi>Eraſm.</hi> Vox orta ex more Graeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum qui por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectis manibus ſuffragia fere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant. <hi>Bez.</hi>
               </note> come together in one place for the Worſhip of God; and ſo to ordain them Elders in <hi>every City,</hi> was to do it in <hi>every Church.</hi> And tho' theſe firſt Ordinations were by <hi>extraordinary Men,</hi> yet the People were not excluded from the juſt right of <hi>chuſing</hi> their own Miniſters; for they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:204450:4"/> were appointed to their Charge, with the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent <hi>Vote and Suffrage of the People.</hi> Howbeit <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> was to preſide in the management of this Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair for their Guidance and Direction, both with reſpect to the Office it ſelf, and their choice of Perſons duly qualified for it.</p>
            <p>In the next place (for the more full opening of the Text) it will be neceſſary briefly to touch upon the <hi>Quality</hi> and <hi>Character</hi> of thoſe Perſons which we here find concerned in the ſetting of things in order in the Churches. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Perſon that imployed <hi>Titus</hi> in this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, <hi>viz. Paul</hi> bears the Character, and had the Office and Authority of an <hi>Apoſtle of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtles had <hi>an immediate and extraordinary Call</hi> to their Office, by God and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: Hence our Apoſtle, when he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent to the <hi>Galatians</hi> the Dignity of his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, that he might recover them to a ſtability in that Doctrine which he had preached to them, tells them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 1. that he was <hi>an Apoſtle, not of Men, neither by Man, but by Jeſus Chriſt, and God the Father.</hi> Ordinary Miniſters, as Paſtors or Elders, tho they were not <hi>of Men;</hi> that is, receive not their Authority from Men, nor are of <hi>humane right</hi> and appointment, yet are they <hi>by Men,</hi> ſo as to be brought to their Office by the Call of the Church; But it was not ſo with the Apoſtles of Chriſt, they were neither of Men nor by Men, but had their Call and Power im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from Chriſt, their Miniſtry being ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:204450:4"/> to the Church, as that by which it was to be planted.</p>
            <p>And as they had an extraordinary Call, ſo were they alſo qualified with extraordinary Gifts and Abilities for the Work they were called to, and had the <hi>infallible guidance</hi> of the Spirit in their Doctrine, which was but neceſſary, ſeeing the Churches were to be founded and built there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 20. The Apoſtles and Prophets of the New Teſtament are <hi>the Foundation,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their Doctrine, tho' Jeſus Chriſt whom they preached, is the only Foundation of the Church, in reſpect of Truſt and Confidence. The Power of the Apoſtles extended to all the Churches, and was equal in them all when they were planted, and therefore <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>The care</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 28.</note> 
               <hi>of all the Churches came upon him daily;</hi> And as a Fruit of this Care in the diſcharge of his Office, he gives forth this Commiſſion to <hi>Titus;</hi> and herein we muſt conſider him as acting by virtue of that Authority which himſelf had received from Chriſt, who is the <hi>firſt Subject, and Head</hi> of all Eccleſiaſtical Power and Juriſdiction; There is no ſuch thing as Authority in or over the Church, but what is derived from Chriſt, who hath all <note place="margin">Mat. 28. 19.</note> Power in Heaven and Earth committed to him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Perſon imployed, <hi>viz. Titus,</hi> had the Character and Office of an <hi>Evangeliſt.</hi> The Evangeliſts were alſo extraordinary Miniſters, (tho' inferior to the Apoſtles) and did uſually attend the motion and direction of the Apoſtles, as aſſiſtant to them in preaching the Goſpel, and ſetling the Churches in due order when firſt plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204450:5"/> And tho' <hi>Titus</hi> be not expreſly called an Evangeliſt, yet if we conſider his Imployment, and compare this Epiſtle to him with thoſe writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to <hi>Timothy,</hi> who is particularly charged to <hi>do the Work of an Evangeliſt,</hi> we ſhall have no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 5.</note> to doubt their being both in the ſame capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: And they acted not as <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Biſhops in their particular Charge, but were ſometimes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in one part of the World, and ſometimes in another, as the Service of the Goſpel required their attendance. And ſince the ceaſing of theſe extraordinary Officers, and the compleating of the Canon of the New Teſtament, all Church-Offices and Affairs are to be regulated and guided by the ordinary and ſtanding Rule of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: And every particular Congregation hath not only <hi>right,</hi> but is in <hi>duty</hi> bound to diſpoſe her ſelf in that Order, and under that Rule and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which Chriſt hath appointed in his Teſtament.</p>
            <p>We ſhall now proceed to thoſe things which our Text, and the preſent Occaſion calls for ſome further diſcourſe of;</p>
            <p>The firſt Inſtance that we have of ſetling Order in a Chriſtian Church, by the ordaining of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Officers therein, is that of the appointment of <hi>Deacons</hi> in the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem, Acts</hi> 6. And this alſo I take to be included in the general Commiſſion here given to <hi>Titus, That he ſhould ſet in order the things that are wanting;</hi> for it appears that the Primitive Churches had both Biſhops, or Elders, and Deacons, ordained in them, when brought to that Settlement and Order which they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:204450:5"/> were to continue in, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 1. And the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of ſuch an Office, and Officers in the Church, when the number of her Members is increaſed, will quickly appear, as it did in the Church at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem;</hi> for, <hi>When the number of the Diſciples</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 6. <hi>v.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>was multiplyed, there aroſe a murmuring of the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> (or Helleniſts) <hi>againſt the Hebrews, becauſe their Widows were neglected in the daily Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Judaei ſie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguebantur; Judaei Paleſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, qui hîc He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braei; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, qui hîc Helleniſtae, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve Graecienſes, qui peculiar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> utebantur dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecto, quam Heileniſticam vocant: <hi>Druſ. vid.</hi> etiam <hi>Grot. &amp; Lightſ.</hi> in locum.</note> The Grecians here mentioned, were not Gentiles, or Greeks by Nation, but ſuch of the ſcattered Jews, who having their Education a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Greeks, and ſpeaking their Language, were called <hi>Hellenists,</hi> in diſtinction from thoſe born and bred up in <hi>Judea,</hi> that ſpake the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Jewiſh Language, which was then a kind of <hi>Chaldaeo-Syriack,</hi> and is called the <hi>Hebrew Tongue,</hi> Acts 22. 2. becauſe of its then common uſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Hebrews or Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> in <hi>Judaea;</hi> and with reſpect to this, <hi>Paul</hi> affirms of himſelf that he was an <hi>Hebrew of the Hebrews,</hi> Phil. 3. 5.</p>
            <p>Now upon this murmuring of the Helleniſts, for the prevention of all diſorder or neglect of this kind for the future; <q>The twelve called the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>V.</hi> 2, 3, 4.</note> multitude of the Diſciples unto them, and told them, That it was unreaſonable for them to be taken off from the more weighty imploiment of preaching the Goſpel to give their attendance upon an Affair of this nature; and therefore that they might be at liberty, to give themſelves continually to Prayer, and the Miniſtry of the Word, and yet the neceſſities of the poor and orderly diſpenſing of the Churches Almes be provided for alſo, They commanded them to look out from among themſelves ſeven Men of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:204450:6"/> honeſt Report, full of the Holy Ghoſt and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom whom they might appoint over this Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; </q> which was accordingly done. This is in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>V.</hi> 5, 6.</note> ſhort the Hiſtory of the firſt Ordination of Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons; and becauſe in this caſe what was firſt in this kind, was to be the Rule and Standard of what ſhould afterwards be done, we ſhall take a review of ſome Paſſages for our preſent Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt;</hi> A Deacon being an ordinary Officer in the Church, appointed to miniſter therein for the <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Non ipſi eligunt ſed multitudini electionem permittunt; qui etiam commodum erant ex illo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum curatione &amp; functione percepturi; atque ipſi eligunt &amp; producunt, &amp; manibus impoſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is ordinant, creant atque decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. <hi>Theoph. in locum.</hi>
               </note> Relief of the Poor; The Election of theſe Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of right belongs to that Congregation where they are to ſerve in this Capacity; And the Holy Apoſtles, tho' veſted with an extraordinary Power, and peculiarly intruſted by Chriſt with the appointment of ſuch an Office and Officers, after they had informed the Church thereabout, and given them a Rule to proceed by, left them to their own voluntary and free choice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> The Number here appointed, <hi>viz. Seven,</hi> was ſuited to the preſent Neceſſity or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience of that numerous Congregation in which they were to miniſter, and is not intended as a Rule, that neither more nor fewer may be appointed in any Congregation after; but that is to be determined by a due comparing of the <hi>End of the Office</hi> with the Circumſtances of each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregation, who are to govern their Choice in point of Number as may beſt anſwer
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204450:6"/> the end, in a ſufficient Proviſion for their preſent neceſſity and comfort of their Poor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly;</hi> The Rule of the Churches proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in her Election is laid before her, in an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of thoſe <hi>Qualifications</hi> which are requiſite in Perſons to be imployed in ſuch a Truſt; They muſt be <hi>Men of honeſt Report;</hi> Men whoſe Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and Holy Life is well atteſted, Perſons of known and approved Integrity, <hi>full of the Holy Ghost, and Wiſdom;</hi> And theſe general Terms are comprehenſive of the Particulars mentioned by our Apoſtle, in that Rule which he hath given about the ſame Matter, in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 8, 9. <hi>Likewiſe muſt the Deacons be grave, not double-tongued, not given to much Wine, not greedy of filthy Lucre, holding the Mystery of the Faith in a pure Conſcience.</hi> And it is an examination and tryal of the Perſons to be choſen by this Rule which the Apoſtle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends in the next words, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. <hi>And let theſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo first be proved, then let them uſe the Office of a Deacon, being found blameleſs.</hi> And this I the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mention, that I may rectify a Miſtake which I think many have taken up from a miſunderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Text, wherein they ſuppoſe that the Apoſtle requires that a Trial ſhould be made of Elders and Deacons in the diſcharge of the proper Work of their Office, before they are ordained to that Office; But this way of Trial is as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign from the Text, as the notion aſſerted is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with it ſelf; for obſerve, He doth not ſay, Try whether they uſe the Office of a Deacon well, (which how can they do before they have it?) and then let them be ordained, if for ſome
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:204450:7"/> time they have acquitted themſelves well in it; But the Trial he requires, is antecedent to their uſing the Office of a Deacon; and is no other than a diligent comparing of the Qualifications of the Perſons, with the Characters of one meet for ſuch an Office which he had before ſet down: This I take to be the plain ſence of the words; And if this be not admitted, we muſt ſuppoſe the Rule of one Apoſtle to contradict the practice of others acting by the ſame infallible Guidance as he wrote, which is abſurd: For it is plain in this of the <hi>Acts,</hi> that they were directed to examine and look into the Qualifications and fitneſs of the Perſons to be choſen for Deacons, before they made choice of them; and that the Apoſtles did by a ſolemn Ordination veſt them with their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, before they acted in it, or uſed the Office of a Deacon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly;</hi> As to the Work of a Deacon, The Care of the Poor is their ſpecial Charge. And in order hereunto, the Contributions and Alms of the Church are to be depoſited with them, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted to their diſtribution, as particular Caſes may require.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now draw to a cloſe of this Point, and paſs on to what remains, when I have ſpoken a word or two.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. To thoſe who are this day ordained and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to the Office of Deacons.</item>
               <item>2. To the Congregation that hath called them to this Office.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:204450:7"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Firſt;</hi> To the Deacons; There are four things that I ſhall recommend to you as neceſſary in the diſcharge of that Truſt that is committed to you, <hi>viz.</hi> Faithfulneſs, Compaſſion, Prudence, and Diligence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Faithfulneſs; You have a Truſt committed to you, <hi>viz.</hi> the Alms and Contributions of the Church, which are indeed a kind of hallowed or dedicated things, and this is a conſiderable Truſt; yea the poor Members of Chriſt, which are dear to him as the Apple of his Eye, are committed to your Care, ſo far as conceres their Relief and Succour in outward things, and this is a greater Truſt; you are in theſe things Stewards for the Church, yea Stewards for Chriſt; and it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of a Steward, that he be found faithful; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider therefore the Duty of your Places, and make Conſcience of a faithful diſcharge thereof, as knowing you muſt give an account to Chriſt, who hath appointed you to this Service, and with him there is no reſpect of Perſons.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Compaſſion; Your Buſineſs and Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, to relieve the Neceſſities of the poor Saints; and this you can never do with a right Spirit, unleſs you have a fellow-feeling with them in their Neceſſities, and do by a gracious Sympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, as it were, put your ſelves in their ſtead; He that gives, muſt do it with chearfulneſs, and that he will never do, if Compaſſion have not firſt filled his Heart; Remember that this Office in the Church, is a Fruit of Chriſt's Pity and Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the Poor; and it is your Duty to make your diſtributions in that manner as may beſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:204450:8"/> the pity and tenderneſs of him whom you ſerve in this Work.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Prudence; Your Pity muſt be guided by Diſcretion; And as it is required that a Deacon ſhould have a plentiful anointing of the good and benign Spirit, that he may be kind and affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately tender towards his Brethren, ſo it is no leſs neceſſary that he be full of Wiſdom alſo, that he may rightly diſcern of the Caſe and Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of thoſe that are to be relieved by him; And that he may carry an equal ballance in his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, between the encouraging of Idleneſs on the one hand, and neglect of the real Diſtreſſes of any on the other; both theſe are extreams to be avoided: And it is certain that there is ſo great a difference in the temper of Perſons, that there will be need of diligent enquiry after the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of ſome, whoſe modeſty would hide them more than is meet, while the unreaſonable impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of others needs a prudent check.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Diligence; It is a Service for Chriſt that you are imployed in, and the Work of the Lord muſt not be done negligently; your Heart muſt be in your Work, and you muſt not do it <hi>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam aliud agens</hi> as by the By, with a ſlight and indifferent Spirit: But as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did the Work of God in his place, whoſe Encomium is, <hi>That in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 31. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>every Work that he began in the Service of the Houſe of God, and in the Law, and Commandments to ſeek his God, he did it with all his Heart:</hi> And know, that your labour ſhall not be in vain in the Lord, for there is no Service (except that which immediately reſpects the ſaving of Mens Souls) more acceptable to Chriſt than that which you are engaged in.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:204450:8"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> To the Congregation; It is your Duty to give reſpect to your Deacons, as eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Service in the Church uſeful and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, <hi>For he that uſeth the Office of a Deacon well,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 13.</note> 
               <hi>purchaſeth to himſelf a good degree, and great bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the Faith which is in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> But eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially your Duty is to incourage them in their Work by a free and plentiful contribution to the Poor, that out of the abundance of thoſe that enjoy plenty, they may always have a ſufficiency to provide for the relief of thoſe that ſuffer want. Many things might be urged for the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your Hearts to ſo good a Work: But my preſent time will not admit of enlargement on this Head.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now proceed to the next thing that lies before us, <hi>viz. The ordaining of Elders in every City or Church;</hi> which was particularly given in Charge unto <hi>Titus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Biſhops or Elders are ordinary Officers in the Church, of <hi>Divine Right</hi> and Appointment, and are to be continued therein to the end of the World; Their Office is ſuperior to that of Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, as more nearly concerning the Good and Edification of the Church, by ſo much as the care and conduct of Mens Souls doth tranſcend the care of the outward Man, and ſupplies of temporal Life. The care which the Apoſtles took for this Proviſion in the Church, we have ſeen ſomething of in the opening of the words, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the method they obſerved in the Calling and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:204450:9"/> Ordaining of Perſons to this Work; it was done, as <hi>Clemens</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the whole Church giving their conſent and approbation: And by their appointment it was, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Clem. Ep.</note> that when the Officers ordained by themſelves were dead, other approved Men ſhould ſucceed in their room, unto whom the Adminiſtration of Holy Things in the Houſe of God was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and by whom the Inſtruction and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church ſhould be duly provided for. We have both the continuance of theſe Officers, and the reaſon of it aſſerted, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 11, 12, 13. <hi>And he gave ſome Apoſtles; and ſome Prophets; and ſome Evangeliſts; and ſome Paſtors and Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers: For the perfecting of the Saints, for the Work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying of the Body of Chriſt: Till we all come in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Faith, and of the Knowledg of the Son of God, unto a perfect Man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt.</hi> Theſe laſt words are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly extended to the compleating of the intire Myſtical Body of Chriſt, and ſo to the period of the diſpenſation of Grace in this World, till there ſhall no longer be a Church on Earth. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' ſome of thoſe Offices and Gifts mentioned in <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. be now ceaſed, yet it is evident others of them muſt continue to the end, until that whereunto a Goſpel Miniſtry is deſigned, be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly accompliſhed: And it very well agrees with the ſcope of the Apoſtle's diſcourſe in this place, to make a joint mention of extraordinary and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Miniſters, ſince they are all given by Chriſt for one and the ſame end, <hi>viz.</hi> the perfecting of his Myſtical Body, which affords a good Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:204450:9"/> for the Union of Chriſtians in their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent meaſures of Attainment, which the Apoſtle is here preſſing them to. The <hi>Apoſtles, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> and <hi>Evangelists,</hi> were of neceſſity to be imployed in the laying of the Foundation of Goſpel-Churches, and the continuance of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Teachers is no leſs neceſſary for the continuance and carrying on of the Spiritual Building of the Church to the end of the World. And there is no reaſon of concluding that all theſe Officers muſt always be in the Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are here mentioned together, no more than there is to affirm that the power of working Miracles ſhould never ceaſe, becauſe the promiſe of ſuch a Power to ſome Believers, is indefinitely given out with the Promiſe of Salvation by Faith in Chriſt, which branch of the Promiſe is certainly extended to all Believers in all Ages, <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 16, 17, 18.</p>
            <p>Now as it is <hi>de facto</hi> evident, that Miracles were for the confirmation of the Goſpel, in the firſt promulgation of it, and are now ceaſed; ſo it is as plain, That the Office and Gifts of Apoſtles, and Prophets, and Evangeliſts, were for the firſt planting of the Churches, and no longer to continue, than till their Order was fully ſetled, and the Revelation of the Mind of God in the New Teſtament perfected, and then the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt ſaw it beſt to leave the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to the Rule of his Written Word, and the guidance of their ordinary Officers according thereto.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:204450:10"/>
            <p> The Officers which we are now treating of, that are in our Text called <hi>Elders,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, are <note place="margin">Adverte eun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Gradum, idemque Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri a <hi>Paulo,</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri, &amp; nomine Epiſcopi.—Neutr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quidem horum eſt nom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinis, ſed poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us officii. <hi>Caje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. in locum.</hi>
               </note> in the very next words ſtilled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Overſeers,</hi> (the like application of both theſe terms to the ſame Perſons and Office you may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in <hi>Act.</hi> 20.) and in the <hi>Epheſ. Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teachers.</hi> And it is evident the Holy Ghoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends no diſtinction, or preeminence of Office among thoſe that bear theſe Characters, by any of theſe different Terms, but they are all ſuited to the ſame Office in its different reſpects: Theſe Miniſters are ſometimes called <hi>Elders,</hi> becauſe of their gravity, and precedency in the Houſe of God, perhaps with ſome reſpect to the Paternal Authority and Preeminence of the Heads of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and Elders of the People amongſt the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> of old; and at other times <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Overſeers,</hi> becauſe their Work is to <hi>take the overſight</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 2.</note> 
               <hi>of the Flock,</hi> and to acquit themſelves as faithful <hi>Watchmen,</hi> who <hi>watch</hi> for the Souls of the People committed to their Truſt, that they may give an account of them to the great Shepherd with joy, and not with grief: And becauſe it is incumbent <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 17.</note> on them <hi>to feed the Church</hi> with the Words of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 28.</note> Life, and to open the Mind of God to them from the Scriptures, that they may by their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry be inſtructed unto his Kingdom; they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſtiled <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our way being thus far prepared by this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Account of the Office of Elderſhip, and the neceſſary continuance of it in the Church, many things do readily offer themſelves as proper to be diſcourſed of under this Head, but (omitting
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:204450:10"/> others) I muſt at preſent confine my ſelf to a brief enquiry after theſe two that follow;</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Qualifications requiſite in the Perſon that performs this Office.</item>
               <item>2. The Relative Duties of an Elder, and the People that he miniſters to.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt;</hi> As to the neceſſary Qualifications of an Elder or Biſhop, they are particularly and fully deſcribed to us, in this of <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 6, 7, 8, 9. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, and 7, verſes. The firſt thing required in both places is, That he be <hi>blameleſs,</hi> not abſolutely without ſin, for there are none ſuch in the World, but free from any notable blemiſh, or ſcandalous offence in his Life, a Man whoſe general carriage and deportment is, to the adorning of that Doctrine which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth himſelf, and muſt teach to others: And then, <hi>the Husband of one Wife;</hi> It is not required that he be a married Man, but ſuppoſing him to be ſo, it is neceſſary that he have been the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band but of one Wife, <hi>viz.</hi> at one time; for tho' he had repented of his Polygamy, yet the note of his former incontinency would ſtick upon him; for Polygamy had no good hearing even amongſt the civilized Heathens; and it was meet that a Biſhop <hi>ſhould have a good Report of them that are without, leſt he fall into reproach, and the ſnare of the Devil:</hi> And this doth alſo include ſuch as had put away their Wives and married others, which was a thing that both the Jews and Gentiles uſed to do, and was utterly forbidden by Chriſt, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in the caſe of Fornication. In like manner
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:204450:11"/> his Children (if he have any) and their courſe of Life under his Family-diſcipline muſt be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; they muſt be <hi>faithful,</hi> not living ſtill in Idolatry and Gentiliſm, but of a ſober well-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned Life, being in ſubjection to him with all gravity; for if it do not appear that he rules his own Houſe well, how ſhall he be eſteemed fit to take care of the Church of God? He muſt alſo be <hi>vigilant,</hi> careful and diligent in his Work and Duty in the ſtation wherein he hath been, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he will be very unmeet for a Paſtoral Charge, which requires perpetual watching; <hi>ſober,</hi> and of a temperate Life, adorned with Modeſty and Moderation, and <hi>of a good behaviour,</hi> full of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, and humanity in all his Deportment, not <hi>ſelf-willed,</hi> proud and heady, no <hi>ſtriker,</hi> nor <hi>ſoon angry,</hi> but a Man that hath good Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Paſſions, and whoſe meekneſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth him to inſtruct and exhort Men <hi>with all Long-ſuffering and Doctrine:</hi> He muſt not <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 24, 25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. 2.</note> 
               <hi>be given to much Wine,</hi> but ſet in himſelf an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Mortification to ſenſual Delights, and utterly deteſt all unjuſt and ſordid ways of heap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up, or keeping Riches for himſelf, as <hi>not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to filthy Lucre,</hi> nor lyable to juſt ſuſpition that he undertakes his Charge, from a baſe cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs of any outward Emoluments belonging thereto, but of a ready Mind, and ſincere Love to Chriſt; and the Souls of Men; and he muſt be <hi>given to Hoſpitality,</hi> that ſo he may go before others in all Offices of Kindneſs and Charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Saints; no <hi>brawler,</hi> litigious or conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Man, but furniſhed both with Abilities and a ready Mind to teach and inſtruct others; and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:204450:11"/> therefore he muſt be well furniſhed with the Knowledg of the Myſteries of God himſelf, <hi>and one that holdeth faſt the faithful Word as he hath been taught, that he may be able by ſound Doctrine both to exhort, and to convince the Gain-ſayers.</hi> In a word, He muſt be a Man <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Juſt</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and a <hi>lover</hi> of all that are ſo; yea, one whoſe vertues Time hath proved and made conſpicuous, a ſteady and well-ſetled Man; <hi>Not a Novice, or new Convert, leſt being lifted up with pride, he fall into the condemnation of the Devil.</hi> This is the Rule of Trial that all Churches are bound to have in their Eye, and diligently to attend to, in their Election of Elders; and when they do ſo, Chriſt approves their choice, and <hi>the Holy Ghost</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 20. 28:</note> 
               <hi>makes their Overſeers;</hi> for both the Gifts, Grace, and Authority of a Goſpel-Miniſter are from him; and no Man or Society of Men under Heaven, can, <hi>de jure,</hi> make him a Miniſter that Chriſt hath not qualified for ſuch a Service; for the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity of all Church Acts depends upon, and is determined by, their conformity to the Rule of Chriſt's Holy Will and Teſtament.</p>
            <p>And as theſe Gifts, Graces, and Vertues, ought to be in ſome good degree viſible in him that is ordained to Elderſhip, before that Charge be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him; ſo after his Ordination it behoves him perpetually to endeavour the giving of a more abundant proof of them in himſelf, by a daily increaſe in their Exerciſe.</p>
            <q>But to proceed;</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> The <hi>Relative Duties</hi> of an Elder and the People are to be conſidered;</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:204450:12"/>
            <p> The due handling of this would require a juſt Treatiſe, but it cannot be expected that I ſhould enlarge upon Particulars, nor indeed ſo much as touch upon many things that do properly belong thereto; But all that I can do, is briefly to ſpeak to ſome things of a general and comprehenſive nature, with ſome inforcement of what may be eſpecially ſeaſonable at this time: And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt;</hi> We ſhall ſpeak to the Duty of an Elder in his place, which is either more <hi>publick,</hi> or more <hi>private;</hi> for in both theſe reſpects, he is under a bond of Duty to Chriſt, and the Souls of the Members of that Church which he miniſters in.</p>
            <p>We ſhall begin with thoſe Duties which are more publickly to be diſcharged by him: And they are;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> To ſtand in ſome reſpects, and to act in ſome things, as a <hi>middle Perſon</hi> betwixt God and the People: Miſtake me not, He is not to be a Mediator between God and the Church, or in his own Intereſt to interpoſe himſelf betwixt God and the People, for the procuring of their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with him; ſuch an Office and Service for the Church no Man on Earth, nor Saint or Angel in Heaven is capable of; The Glory of it is Chriſt's peculiar: As there is but one God, ſo <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 5.</note> in this regard, there is but <hi>one Mediator betwixt God and Men, the Man Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> But in two reſpects a Miniſter ſtands between God and the People;</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:204450:12"/> 1. As he is to be the Mouth of the People un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and to go before them, in the Exerciſe of thoſe Gifts and Graces which Chriſt hath fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed him with, in conceiving, and pouring out the <hi>publick Prayers</hi> of the Church to the moſt High. And by ſome this is taken to be the ſpecial import of that ſaying of the Apoſtle's, in <hi>Act.</hi> 6. 4. <hi>But we will give our ſelves continually</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aſſidui erimus tum in prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundo plebi in precibus ad Deum, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um in Plebe inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda. <hi>Grot. in locum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to Prayer, and to the Miniſtry of the Word;</hi> They ſeem equally to reſpect in both (viz. <hi>Prayer,</hi> and the <hi>Miniſtry of the Word)</hi> the <hi>publick diſcharge</hi> of their Office in the Church; and there is no doubt but what is here mentioned, continues to be the Duty of ordinary Miniſters in their Station, as much as it was theirs. And the Scripture knows no other Proviſion for the orderly and profitable performance of this Service in the Church, than what Chriſt hath made by enduing Perſons with thoſe Gifts, and ſuch an anointing of his Holy Spirit, as may enable them to go before their Brethren therein. It would be very ſad to have the Souls of Men committed to the care of ſuch as are ſo unacquainted with, or inſenſible of, their Spiritual Concerns, as not to be in ſome good degree prepared for this part of their Work, to be the Mouth of the People, in pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring out their ſolemn publick Prayers unto God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As he is to be the Mouth of God to the People, to deliver his Meſſage from God, and ſpeak to them in his Name. It is eminently the Work and Buſineſs of a Paſtor, To <hi>preach the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Word, to be inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, to</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:204450:13"/> 
               <hi>reprove, rebuke, and exhort with all Long-ſuffering and Doctrine;</hi> They are Miniſters of the New Teſtament, and God's Ambaſſadors unto Men, who are to diſpenſe the Myſteries of God to his Church, and they ought to exerciſe all diligence herein, <hi>Studying to approve themſelves VVorkmen</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 14, 15</note> 
               <hi>that need not to be aſhamed, rightly dividing the Word of Truth:</hi> And woe will be to him that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes this Charge, and preacheth not the Goſpel; which is the ſincere Milk, and Spiritual Food that the Souls of his Flock ought continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to be fed with.</p>
            <p>This Duty is ſo earneſtly preſſed upon all Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions <note place="margin">Oportet Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copum praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantem mori.</note> where theſe Things are treated of in the Scriptures, that there is no need of any other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to enforce it, but what are obvious to every one's Eye in the reading of them; And he deſerves not the Name of a Miniſter, Paſtor, or Biſhop, that labours not herein.</p>
            <p>It will not (I ſuppoſe) be expected that I ſhould here lay down Rules for Preaching, or enter into a Diſcourſe about the Method of Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical Studies in order thereunto: Only give me leave at preſent to recommend three things to thoſe that are under ſo ſtrict and ſolemn a Charge to preach the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let your Care be, to deal with the Souls and Conſciences of Men, as knowing that it is the Salvation of Souls which you are to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour after, a Care of Souls that is committed to you, and an account of them that you muſt make to God: It is not your Buſineſs to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:204450:13"/> the itching Ears or wanton Fancies of Men, <note place="margin">Jerome <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of ſome in his Time; That,</hi> Id ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent curae, non quomodo Scripturarum medullas ebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, ſed quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo aures Populi decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matorum floſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis mulce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant.</note> but to ſpeak to their Hearts, and <hi>by manifeſtation of the Truth, to recommend your ſelves to every Man's Conſcience in the ſight of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 4. 2. Lay out your pains in a ſolid explaining of the Principles of Religion, and a judicious accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation of them to practice; that ſincere Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the power of Godlineſs, may be promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by your Miniſtry: Preſs the particular Duties of Men in every Relation and Capacity upon them, warn them of the ſleights of Satan; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke their Errors and Diſorders, that go aſtray; comfort the Afflicted and broken in Heart; And in theſe things, let no Zeal, Diligence, Boldneſs, Induſtry or Labour be wanting.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That this may be accompliſhed; Be ſure that you ſpeak <hi>as the Oracles of God;</hi> and deliver that <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 11.</note> Doctrine to the People which is drawn from the pure Fountain of God's Word. It is no leſs than the Evidence of Divine Authority, that will work upon the Soul; and command the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of a Man; whether it be by way of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, Exhortation, or Reproof, it is the ſtamp of Heaven upon the Things delivered by you that renders them powerful; Let it therefore be your principal care in Preaching, clearly, to open, and pertinently to apply the Scriptures, that your Hearers may bear away this Conviction from your Sermons, <hi>That you have the Mind of Chriſt.</hi> It is not enough that the things you ſpeak be true, but you muſt manifeſt them to be ſo by ſtrong and convincing Proofs. Make Conſcience of giving, what in you lies, the very ſence of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:204450:14"/> Holy Ghoſt in the Scriptures that you ſpeak to; and weaken not excellent Truths, by wringing them out of ſuch Texts as intend another thing: The word of God is Sacred, and muſt be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with all religious reſpect and reverence. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Things will admit of no trifling.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Remember that the Duty of your Place is, <hi>Not to preach your ſelves but Chriſt Jeſus the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Lord;</hi> His Glory muſt be the Mark aimed at by all your Labours, and his Grace the principal Subject of all your Diſcourſes; It is not a Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophick Harangue that will ſave the Souls of Men, but the <hi>preaching of Chriſt Crucified;</hi> His <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 23.</note> Goſpel is the <hi>Power of God unto Salvation to them</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 16.</note> 
               <hi>that believe;</hi> and his Holy Name is the Ointment that perfumes all Religious Exerciſes; Therefore I will not only ſay, Let there be <hi>Aliquid Chriſti,</hi> ſomething of Chriſt in every Sermon, but let Chriſt be the beginning, middle, and end of your Diſcourſes; for in him are hid <hi>all the Treaſures of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Coloſ. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Wiſdom and Knowledg;</hi> in him is the Fountain and Head-ſpring of all true Comfort and Holineſs. So much for the firſt Thing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> Unto the publick Work and Charge of a Biſhop or Elder, belongs alſo the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sacraments, or Ordinances of poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Inſtitution in the Church; as Baptiſm, and the Lord's Supper; This appertains to that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation of the Myſteries of God that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him, and to that feeding of the Sheep of Chriſt which is required of him. And then,</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:204450:14"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>3dly.</hi> It is his Duty to take care of the due ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of <hi>Diſcipline</hi> in the Church, and the right ordering of all things pertaining to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof; He is the <hi>Overſeer</hi> of God's Houſe, <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 17.</note> and is to <hi>rule</hi> therein, not in a deſpotical or lordly Way, but by the Teſtament of Chriſt, as becomes a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> and as one ſet over the <hi>Lord's Heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage</hi> who are a voluntary People, and to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned not with force and rigor, but with their own conſent. All the Brethren have an Intereſt in the management of Church-Affairs, in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and ejection of Members; yet this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies not a peculiar Concernment of the Elder in theſe things, and a neglect of their due Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration will eſpecially be charged upon him, if guilty thereof. And in theſe things, great Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Tenderneſs, Diligence, and Impartiality is required of him. It is a Matter of great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, that the Gates of the Lord's Houſe, the goings out and comings in thereof be well look'd to. If Members be not received with due cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, our Number may be increaſed, but not our Joy, and if any be precipitantly, and without juſt grounds ejected, the ſcandal and inconvenience will be as great.</p>
            <p>And in all theſe things, an Elder muſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour ſo to demean himſelf, that in the whole courſe of his Miniſtry, there may be kept up a very lively repreſentation of the Love, Care, Wiſdom, Compaſſion, Faithfulneſs, and Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt whom he ſerves.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:204450:15"/>
            <p> I ſhall ſay no more of thoſe Duties that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent on a Paſtor in the publick Exerciſe of his Miniſtry: But in the next place;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> There are alſo Duties of great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to the Souls of Men, which an Elder is bound diligently to attend the diſcharge of in a more private and particular way. He is obliged to a conſtant watchfulneſs for, and over his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ought diligently to enquire and ſearch into the ſtate of his Flock; That thoſe who are in danger to err for want of counſel may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected; the unruly warned and rebuked; feeble and dejected Souls ſtrengthened, comforted, and encouraged; and thoſe that are beſet with Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and Temptations, ſuccoured and relieved. Unto an unwearied diligence in theſe things, <hi>Paul</hi> excites the Elders of the Church at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> by his own Example; <hi>You know</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>how I kept</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 20. 18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>back nothing that was profitable for you, but have ſhewed you, and have taught you publickly, and from Houſe to Houſe.</hi> The like he doth to thoſe of <hi>Theſſalonioa,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 2. 10, 11, 12. <hi>Ye are Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and God alſo, how holily, and juſtly, and unblameably, we behaved our ſelves among you that believe: As you know how we exhorted, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, and charged every one of you, (as a Father doth his Children) That you would walk worthy of God,</hi> &amp;c. And again, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 28, 29. <hi>Whom (viz.</hi> Chriſt) <hi>we preach, warning every Man, and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every Man in all wiſdom, (i. e.</hi> by a ſuitable ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying of Things to them according to their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:204450:15"/> Circumſtances and Conditions) <hi>that we may preſent every Man perfect in Chriſt Jeſus; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto I alſo labour,</hi> &amp;c. And all this pains muſt be enlivened by an <hi>Holy Example;</hi> for if a Miniſter does not live over the Inſtructions he gives to others, and appear a burning and ſhining Light in Life and Converſation, as well as in Doctrine, his ill Manners will do more hurt, than all his Words can ever do good: Examples have the greateſt influence upon Men; <hi>Verba docent, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empla trahunt;</hi> Therefore is that charge ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently repeated, That they ſhould in all things be <hi>Enſamples</hi> to the Flock.</p>
            <p>I will add but a word or two for the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement and quickening of a Paſtor to his Duty; and then paſs on to what remains. What I intend at preſent, I ſhall ſum up under two Heads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt;</hi> Conſider whom you ſerve, and by whoſe Authority you are to act in your place: You are a Miniſter of Chriſt, not a Creature of humane appointment; It is by the Holy Ghoſt that you are made an Overſeer, therefore take heed to your ſelf, and to the Flock of God. A like Argument or Motive is included in that of <hi>Col.</hi> 4. 17. <hi>Say to</hi> Archippus, <hi>Take heed to the Miniſtry that thou hast received in the Lord, that thou fulfil it.</hi> To receive a Miniſtry in the Lord, is to be imployed in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice for Chriſt, and by his Order and Authority. Now from hence theſe things (and others like to them) may be inferred:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there is a real dignity and worth in the Office which you are to adminiſter; <hi>He that deſires</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:204450:16"/> 
               <hi>the Office of a Biſhop</hi> (ſaith our Apoſtle) <hi>deſires a good Work:</hi> It is an Office that a Man muſt labour in, but his Labour is in a <hi>good Work, viz.</hi> that which is honourable as well as uſeful, as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies; and you know <hi>Difficilia quae pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chra,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> honourable Imployments are not without their burden. Men may deſpiſe this Function, but let not that diſcourage you; Chriſt hath ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured you, and let the ſenſe of Duty and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to him, bear you above all Diſcouragements to a faithful diſcharge of your Truſt, and that with holy boldneſs, and fortitude of Mind.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If you have reeived your Office from Chriſt, you muſt be reſponſible to him for the diſcharge of it; Stewards muſt one day give an account to their Lord; and thrice happy he, to whom Chriſt ſhall ſay in the day of Account, <hi>Well done thou good and faithful Servant; enter thou into the Joy of thy Lord.</hi> There is nothing tends more to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage us to all diligence and faithfulneſs in our Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, than a deep and fixed thoughtfulneſs of that <hi>ſolemn Audit</hi> which we muſt be brought to, at the Kingdom and Appearing of the great Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thoſe that Chriſt imploys in his Work, may expect his gracious preſence and aſſiſtance in all the difficulties that do attend it; For this we have his word paſſed; <hi>Lo, I am with you to the end of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 28 <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the VVorld;</hi> tho' you may be perſecuted, you ſhall never be <hi>forſaken</hi> of me; and tho' your Burthen may ſometimes preſs you with a great weight, yet my ſtrength ſhall be made perfect in your weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and my <hi>Grace ſhall always be ſufficient for you.</hi> It is the Grace and Aſſiſtance of Chriſt that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:204450:16"/> a Miniſter muſt depend upon, and expect the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of his Labours from; and having ground for ſuch an expectation, let him not faint from the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of any hardſhip or oppoſition that may lie in his way; for all Power in Heaven and Earth is in his Hand, by whom he is imployed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Seeing he is ingaged in Chriſt's Service, the Reward of Faithfulneſs therein is ſure; Chriſt will not fail to ſhew himſelf a bountiful Lord and Maſter to thoſe that ſerve him: None ever were, or ſhall be loſers by doing his Work. This is the incouragement that <hi>Peter</hi> lays before the Elders of the Church, and exhorts them to lift up their Hearts to; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 4. <hi>And when the chief Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd ſhall appear, ye ſhall receive a Crown of Glory that fadeth not away:</hi> And this will be a ſufficient compenſation of all your ſorrow and travel here. Look how much your labour hath been more than others, God will cloath you with the brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Rays of Glory; your Converts ſhall then be your Crown and your Joy, when <hi>they that have turned many to Righteouſneſs, ſhall ſhine as the Stars for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> Conſider, That it is the Care and Charge of Souls that is committed to you; not the Temporal Concerns of this Life, but the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of Eternal Life are the Buſineſs of your Stewardſhip: Now one Soul is of more worth than all the World, becauſe immortal, and made for an Eternal State: The Influence that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of the Word hath into the future ſtate of Men, made <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, as in an extaſie, <hi>VVho is ſufficient for theſe Things!</hi> They are the Souls of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:204450:17"/> Men that God thought it worth the giving of his own Son to redeem, and Chriſt thought not much to ſhed his precious Blood for; the Church is a Society of Men which God hath purchaſed to himſelf by his own Blood, and now committed to your Care, and appointed you to watch for their Souls, therefore take heed to your ſelves, and to your Flock; for if any of them periſh in an evil way thro' your neglect of Duty towards them, They die in their ſins, but God will require their Blood at your Hand.</p>
            <p>We come now to the laſt thing that lies before us, <hi>viz. The Duty of the People towards their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Able and faithful Paſtors are a great Bleſſing, and ſpecial Fruit of Chriſt's Love to his Church, and he as well expects and requires her improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſo great a Talent, and the chearful per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of her Duty towards her Miniſters, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he doth ſtrictly charge them to acquit themſelves with all fidelity and diligence in their places. I am under a neceſſity of bringing this part of my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe into a narrow compaſs; and therefore ſhall recommend to you but theſe four things:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> You owe to your Paſtor great Love, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and Honour, for his Work-ſake; And God requires that you make a due paiment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: This our Apoſtle often preſſeth with great earneſtneſs; for inſtance ſee 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 12, 13. <hi>And we beſeech you, Brethren, to know</hi> (that is, to acknowledg with due reſpect) <hi>them which labour among you, and are over you in the Lord, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:204450:17"/> 
               <hi>you, and to eſteem them very highly in love for their Work-ſake.</hi> And again; <hi>Let the Elders that Rule well, be counted worthy of double Honour, eſpecially thoſe that labour in the Word and Doctrine,</hi> 1 Tim. 5. 17. If you have a true Friend in the World, it is he that watcheth for your Souls, tells you the Truth, and travels night and day to preſent you perfect unto God: And let not his faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in admoniſhing you, cauſe an abatement of your love to him; but if you love your own Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, let it rather raiſe your eſteem of him; No wiſe Man will hate his Phyſician for giving a bitter Potion when his Life is ſaved by it, or a Chirurgeon, for performing an Operation painful to him, when the reſtoring or preſerving of a Member of his Body depends thereon. He that brings to you the good Tidings of Salvation, and publiſheth Peace, deſerves to have his Feet eſteemed beautiful, and to be received with the Love and Reſpect that's due to ſo good a Meſſage, and the bringer of it: Chriſt will not bear the contempt of his Meſſengers, therefore take heed that you provoke him not, by caſting a ſcornful Eye upon them; nor rob your own Souls of the benefit of their Miniſtry, by entertaining evil Surmiſes, or undue Prejudices againſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> You owe <hi>Submiſſion</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> to them in the diſcharge of their Office, and in the exerciſe of that Rule and Overſight which Chriſt hath committed to them for your Edification; <hi>Obey them that have the Rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves,</hi> Heb. 13. 17. It is not a blind Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:204450:18"/> that the Apoſtle requires, nor ſuch as ſhall ſuppoſe a Legiſlative Power in Church-Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, but an orderly ſubjection to them acting in their Office according to the Law and Teſtament of Jeſus Chriſt; even a ready obedience to the Word of God diſpenſed by them, and humble ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to their juſt Reproofs and Miniſterial Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, when rendred neceſſary by any miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; and this either in the publick or more pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate diſcharge of their Truſt. God doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire that Men ſhould pull out their own Eyes, and mancipate themſelves to the conduct of Church-Officers, without the exerciſe of their own Reaſon and Judgment, as it is in the Papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, where the blind lead the blind, till both fall into the Ditch. But when the Law of Chriſt is obſerved, and a conformity with that urged, by the evidence and demonſtration of Truth from the Holy Scriptures, herein the Obedience of the People is juſtly expected; and he that thinks himſelf too good, or too wiſe, to receive Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or ſubmit to Reproof from his Paſtor, ill deſerves a place in any Chriſtian Congregation. <hi>My Brethren,</hi> take heed of a proud factious Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; <note place="margin">James 3. 1.</note> 
               <hi>be not many Maſters, knowing that we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the greater Condemnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as it is your Duty to receive the Doctrine of Chriſt diſpenſed by them with meekneſs and fear, and with humility to ſubmit to the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline which they exerciſe, according to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority they have received from Chriſt; ſo alſo ought you to propoſe their holy Example for your imitation; Heb. 13. 7. <hi>Remember them</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:204450:18"/> 
               <hi>which have the Rule over you, who have ſpoken to you the Word of God whoſe Faith follow, conſidering the end of their Converſation.</hi> Be followers of them as they are of Chriſt; for if it be their Duty to be Enſamples to their Brethren, <hi>in Word, in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 12.</note> 
               <hi>in Charity, in Spirit, in Faith, in Purity;</hi> it muſt be no leſs the Duty of their Brethren to write after their Copy, and conform to their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in all theſe Things. For if the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of this Office be not improved by the Church unto their Edification and real growth in Grace and Holineſs, the end of it, as to them, is utterly loſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> You are much concerned to continue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in Prayer to God for them: You know the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> often recommends himſelf to the Prayers of the Church; and if he thought them ſo neceſſary for his help, we have much more reaſon to account them ſo for ours. The temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of Miniſters are many; they have great Difficulties and Diſcouragements to conflict with; And their Work is ſuch, as they can never fill up their Places as they ought, but by the ſpecial Aid and Aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt; the ſucceſs of all their Labours depends upon a Divine Bleſſing, and the preſence of God with them; and in theſe things both the Glory of Chriſt, and the Comfort and Edification of your own Souls is nearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned; which is a ſufficient Reaſon for your making Conſcience of this Duty.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:204450:19"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>4thly.</hi> You are bound, according to your Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, to provide a comfortable and honourable Maintenance for them. <hi>Let him that is taught, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with him that teacheth IN ALL GOOD THINGS; Be not deceived, God is not mocked, Gal.</hi> 6. 6, 7. Theſe words call not only for a Maintenance of Miniſters, but for ſuch a plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Contribution as may make them partakers with you <hi>in all good Things:</hi> If God bleſs the Congregation with a plentiful Portion of this World's Goods, it is their Duty to make their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter a Party with them in their flouriſhing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; and conſidering the Place and Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he is in; and the Service he attends, it would be extreamly unworthy to think you have done enough if his preſſing Neceſſities be anſwered, while you abound in Superfluities. If the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation be Poor, their Miniſter muſt be content to be poor with them, yea, rejoyce to approve himſelf a Miniſter of Chriſt by hunger and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, if the Providence of God call him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: But while it is in the Power of your Hand to provide better for him, God expects it from you; and, <hi>be not deceived, he is not mocked,</hi> neither will he ſuffer his Commands to be ſlighted and evaded, without rendring a juſt rebuke to the Offender; <hi>For whatſoever a Man ſoweth, that ſhall he alſo reap.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that you may the better underſtand how far you are concerned in this Duty, before I proceed to the farther preſſing of it, let me
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:204450:19"/> put you in remembrance;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That a Miniſter is bound to attend wholly and only upon his Calling in the Miniſtry, and not to entangle himſelf in the Affairs of this Life, that he may pleaſe him by whom he is called to this Spiritual Warfare; and nothing but real Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity may diſpenſe with the contrary; his whole Time and Strength is little enough to be imployed in the Work he is called to; he muſt give himſelf to the Miniſtry of the Word and Prayer, and continue in Reading, Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as a Man wholly devoted unto Goſpel-Service; and is therefore by his Call to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, ſecluded from thoſe Ways and Means of providing for his own Subſiſtence, as the Trades and ſecular Imployments of others furniſh them with; that his Mind, by the cares of worldly Buſineſs, may not be diverted from that ſtudy of God's Word, and Care of Souls, which the duty of his Station engageth him to: And if he may not expoſe himſelf to the careful Thoughts that accompany worldly Buſineſs, tho' tending to his profit: Certainly it is no way meet that he ſhould be left to conflict with the thorny Cares of a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitous Condition, while thoſe he miniſters to have Means to prevent it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is no leſs the Duty of a Miniſter, than of other Men, to provide for his Family, and (what lies in him) to take care of his Wife and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 8.</note> that they may not be left expoſed to a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Miſeries and Temptations when he is gone. I confeſs, of all Men in the World, a covetous raking Temper worſt becomes a Miniſter; but
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:204450:20"/> we greatly miſtake, if we think he muſt diveſt himſelf of the due Affection of an Huſband to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Wife, or of a Father towards his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; or that thoſe Fruits thereof, which are juſtly eſteemed commendable in others, ſhould be a fault in him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. An Elder or Biſhop is under a ſpecial Charge to uſe Hoſpitality, and to ſet in himſelf a pattern of Charity and compaſſionate Bounty to poor Souls: And if it be his Duty to be hoſpitable and charitable in an eminent degree, then without Controverſy the People are concerned to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that he may be capable of giving proof of this Grace in him, by the exerciſe of it as there is occaſion.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being premiſed, I ſhall ſhew you, that you lie under the ſtrongeſt Obligation ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable to this Duty.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. By the Eternal Law of Nature.</item>
               <item>2. By the expreſs Command and Appointment of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>3. On the account of the great and manifeſt Evil and Inconvenience that follows the neglect thereof.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt;</hi> The Law and Light of Nature obligeth you to it, as to the matter of Equity and Juſtice. And from hence our Apoſtle takes his firſt Plea, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 7, &amp;c. <hi>Who goeth a Warfare any time at his own Charges? Who planteth a Vineyard, and eateth not of the Fruit thereof? Or who feedeth a</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:204450:20"/> 
               <hi>Flock, and eateth not of the Milk of the Flock?</hi> The Miniſtry is a Warfare, undertaken at the Command of Chriſt, for the Service of your Souls; and it is as reaſonable that the Miniſter ſhould receive a ſupply of outward things from you, as it is that a faithful Souldier ſhould receive his Pay from his Captain at the charge of the Common-wealth, for whoſe good he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mlitates. Shall a Man feed a Flock (as a Paſtor does) and be denied to eat of the Milk of that Flock, which it is his work to keep and feed? Or is it conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with common Juſtice, to deprive a Man of the Fruit of that Vineyard which is planted and manured by his own Labour? Such is the caſe in reſpect of Maintenance between a Miniſter and the People; It is not your Charity that I ask for him, but <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Debt</hi> that I plead for; He is imployed in your Service, and of right ſhould live upon your Charge. Nay, you have called him off from other Buſineſs, and therefore his Maintenance is as due from you as is the Wages of your Servant; tho' I fear ſome give more to the meaneſt Servant in their Houſe, than they are willing to do to their Miniſter. Certainly, if you chuſe as you ought, your Miniſters are not of the <hi>lowest of the People,</hi> but may be allowed to have a ſhare of Parts, common Prudence, and Ability for Buſineſs, with other Men; and could manage Trades, or fall into other Imployments, and get Eſtates as well as you, if they were not <hi>devoted to a better Service;</hi> and muſt they needs be devoted to Neceſſities and Miſery in the ſame hour that they enter upon the Miniſtry? My Brethren, this
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:204450:21"/> ought not to be; Let your Miniſters have as good treatment at leaſt, as <hi>the Law</hi> provided for the <hi>Ox</hi> that <hi>trode out the Corn,</hi> who might not be <hi>muzled:</hi> Neither was this written for the ſake of Oxen; for, <hi>Doth God take care of Oxen?</hi> Or was there no higher end of this Law, than that the Bruit Creature ſhould not be abuſed? Certainly there was; and <hi>for our ſakes, no doubt, was this writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>That he that ploweth ſhould plow in hope, and that he that threſheth in hope, ſhould be partaker of his hope.</hi> For, <hi>If we have ſown unto you Spiritual Things, is it a great thing if we ſhall reap your Carnal Things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> The Lord hath not left us to argue this only from general Principles of Reaſon and common Equity, but, to put the Matter beyond diſpute, hath ſuperadded his <hi>expreſs Command:</hi> Thus he provided for his Miniſters in the Time of the Law, which the Apoſtle urgeth in the next place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 13. <hi>Do ye not know that they which miniſter about Holy Things, live of the Things of the Temple? And they which wait at the Altar, are partakers with the Altar?</hi> God did no ſooner ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the <hi>Levites</hi> to the Service of his Sanctuary, but he by Law provided for their Subſiſtence: And tho' they were but one Tribe in twelve, yet the Tenth of the Increaſe of the whole Land was given to them, beſides the Firſt-Fruits and Offerings, and divers other Advantages; ſo that their Lot might equal, yea, exceed that of their Brethren. This Law indeed is now abrogated, and we pretend to no right of Tything your
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:204450:21"/> Eſtates; but the moral Equity of it can never ceaſe, neither hath Chriſt left Goſpel-Miniſters to the wide World, but hath made proviſion for them alſo, ſo far as the intereſt of his Command will go with them that profeſs his Name; for ſo it follows, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>Even ſo hath the Lord ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that they that preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi> The <hi>Labourer</hi> is ſtill <hi>worthy</hi> of his <hi>Hire,</hi> and not the <hi>leſs worthy</hi> becauſe he <hi>labours in the Goſpel;</hi> Tho' indeed (if Men did fully come up to their Duty, yet ſtill) the Charge of Goſpel-Worſhip will appear very inconſiderable when compared with that of the Law; for, were that my Buſineſs, I think I could demonſtrate that the fifth part of their Eſtates was yearly to be ſpent in things relating to the Temple-Service. And if we are ſenſible of the great Priviledg and Bleſſing of the Goſpel, on higher accounts than meerly the caſe of thoſe Burthens, we ſhall never think much to defray the moderate Charge of a Goſpel-Miniſtry, in ſuch a manner as may give a Reputation to our Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly;</hi> That you may prevent the <hi>evil</hi> and <hi>inconvenience</hi> that follows the neglect of this Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, it concerns you chearfully to practiſe it; I might have ſaid <hi>Evils</hi> and <hi>Inconveniences</hi> as of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; for <hi>many</hi> there are, and thoſe of eaſy obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to an unprejudiced Eye; but it is <hi>the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of Study</hi> which at preſent I chiefly aim at; That Study muſt needs be diſcouraged (I intend the ſtudy of Theology) by the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples neglect to make a comfortable Proviſion for
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:204450:22"/> their Miniſters, is too evident to require a Proof; who will apply himſelf to gather and lay up thoſe Stores of ſolid Learning which are needful to a Miniſter, when he can expect to purchaſe nothing to himſelf but Poverty and Diſtreſs thereby? Or how ſhall a Miniſter be capable to furniſh himſelf with the <hi>univerſal knowledg</hi> of Things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to his Work, that hath no Means of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for his own Information, or no Time free from Cares and worldly Buſineſs? And the diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of this will at laſt fall to the ſhare of the People that he miniſters to. He that conſiders that the Holy Scriptures are originally written in <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek,</hi> muſt have a hard Forehead if he deny the uſefulneſs of Learning to a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; beſides, many other things there are that call for it, in reference to the opening of the Scriptures, which I cannot now inſiſt upon: And it is not without diligent and continual ſtudy, that the deep Things of God can be ſearched out, and ſo propoſed to you, as to enrich your Minds with the clear and ſolid knowledg of them. I confeſs, a little Learning, and leſs Study, may furniſh a Man with ſuch a Diſcourſe as may pleaſe ſome weak Perſons, that judg of a Sermon by the loudneſs of the Voice, and affectionate Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; or that can fancy themſelves to be fed with the Aſhes of jingling Words, and Cadency of terms in a Diſcourſe: But alas! the ſeeming warmth of Affection that is ſtirred by ſuch means, is as ſhort-liv'd as a Land-Flood that has no Spring to feed it. He that will do the Souls of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple good, and approve himſelf a <hi>Paſtor after</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jer. 3. 15.</note>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:204450:22"/> 
               <hi>God's Heart,</hi> muſt <hi>feed them with Knowledg and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> and endeavour to maintain a conſtant Zeal and Affection in them, by well-informing their Judgments, and ſuch an opening of the Mind of God from the Scriptures, as may command their Conſciences: And this is not to be expected, but from him that labours in his Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy as well as in his Pulpit. Miſtake me not! I know the ſucceſs, and Fruit of all the ſtudies and labours of him that preacheth the Goſpel, is from the Grace and Power of the Holy Ghoſt; but <hi>the aſſistance of the Spirit</hi> is to be expected by us <hi>in the way of our Duty.</hi> Theſe things might be yet applied more home to my preſent purpoſe; but perhaps ſome will think there is too much ſaid al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready (tho' I heartily wiſh more were not need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful) and my Time calls me to put a period to this Exerciſe. And therefore I will only add a word for the enforcement of this and the other Duties which I have laid before you, by accommodating the ſame things to you, that were before touched, for the encouragement and quickning of your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor in his Duty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt;</hi> Remember that your Paſtor is <hi>the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Chriſt,</hi> one that diſpenſeth the Myſteries of God to you in his Name; and therefore (he acting in his Place, according to his Duty) the Lord Jeſus will account that done to himſelf, that is done to his Miniſter; <hi>He that receiveth you</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 40. <hi>with</hi> Luk. 10. 16.</note> (ſaith he) <hi>receiveth me; and he that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me,</hi> &amp;c. If the <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of Chriſt will beget an <hi>awe</hi> in you, or his matchleſs
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:204450:23"/> and unſpeakable Love influence you, there is no want of <hi>Motives</hi> to thoſe Duties that have been preſt upon you: If you acknowledg a religious Reſpect and Reverence due to the Son of God, exerciſe it in humble obedience to his Word: And if you love him, and value his Goſpel, treat not his Miniſters in an unworthy manner; and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not, That he who gave his Life a Ranſom for you, well deſerves a return of the greateſt love from you, and to be <hi>honoured</hi> by you, not only with good words, but <hi>with your Subſtance, and the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 3. 9.</note> 
               <hi>firſt Fruits of all your Increaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> 'Tis the Buſineſs of <hi>your Salvation,</hi> and the Concern of <hi>your precious and immortal Souls</hi> that a Miniſter is imployed in; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is much more your own Intereſt than his, that you ſhould make Conſcience of your Duty; with this Argument the Apoſtle enforces his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 17. <hi>For they watch for your Souls, as they that must give an account, that they may do it with Joy, and not with Grief; for that is unprofitable for you.</hi> The Miniſtry can never be effectual to the ſaving of your Souls, if you be not ſincere in Obedience under it. And will you be leſs careful for your Souls, and their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Welfare, than you are for your Bodies, and the Comforts of a Temporal Life? Can you be content to lay out your Strength and Subſtance to provide for theſe, and neglect the other? It is ſad to conſider how many there are among Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors that live in <hi>this World,</hi> as if there were no truth in the Report of <hi>that which is to come;</hi> and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:204450:23"/> have the meaneſt eſteem of the moſt neceſſary means of Salvation, <hi>viz.</hi> the Word, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt, and a Goſpel-Miniſtry: Many there are, that beſides a Proviſion of Neceſſaries, can expend perhaps an hundred pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> more or leſs, for the Convenience, Ornament, or Delight of a frail Carcaſs, that will grudg half ſo much for the Poor, or the ſupport of Goſpel-Worſhip: If their Bodies be afflicted, it is not five, ten, or twenty pounds that they think too much for a Phyſician, in recompence of his skill and care about them; when it may be they can ſcarce afford half ſo much to him that continually ſtudies and travels to promote the Cure and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their ſick Souls: But when Men come to be thro'ly poſſeſt, That Eternity is no Fiction, and the Goſpel is the only means of eſcaping the Wrath to come, and inheriting Eternal Glory, they will take other meaſures about theſe things.</p>
            <p>To conclude: We have ſeen ſomething of thoſe gracious Proviſions that Chriſt in his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Faithfulneſs hath made for his Church, in the appointment of Deacons for the refreſhing of the Bowels of the Poor, and Paſtors for the guidance and nouriſhment of your Souls unto Eternal Life: We have heard ſomething alſo of the Duty he expects both from the Officers and Members in his Church to the end of the World: What now remains, But that we all in our places make Conſcience of living over his Commands, (for if we know theſe things, happy are we if we do them) and practically acknowledg his
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:204450:24"/> Love and Faithfulneſs, with a conſtant admiration of his Grace, and the return of hearty Praiſes to him for all theſe Fruits of it: Which that you may do, <hi>The God of Peace that brought again from</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>the Dead our Lord Jeſus, that great Shepherd of the Sheep, thro' the Blood of the Everlaſting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, Make you perfect in every good Work, to do his Will, working in you that which is well-pleaſing in his ſight, thro' Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be Glory for ever and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:204450:24"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Theſe Books following are printed for</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Fabian, <hi>at the Sign of the Bible in St.</hi> Paul<hi>'s Church-Yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Works of <hi>Joſephus</hi> with Cuts. <hi>Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Packet of Letters. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Gentleman's Recreation with Cuts. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Drummond</hi>'s Hiſtory of <hi>Scotland;</hi> Containing the Lives and Reigns of <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, the 2<hi>d,</hi> the 3<hi>d,</hi> the <hi>4th,</hi> the <hi>5th;</hi> with ſeveral Memorials of State during the Reigns of <hi>James</hi> the Sixth, and <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, with their Effigies. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of Friendſhip. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vincent</hi>'s Diſcourſe of Chriſt's certain and ſuddain appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to Judgement. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Flavell</hi>'s Navigation Spiritualized. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſop</hi>'s Fables in Engliſh. 12<hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The downfal of ſeveral Great Men, or Popiſh Plottings, not to be parallel'd in former Ages; being a Seaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Warning for the Times. 12<hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robinſon</hi>'s Learning-Foundation; teaching to Spell and to Read Engliſh. 12<hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
